<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Micro Binfie Virtual Conference 2020]]></title><description><![CDATA[An online seminar series chaired by the Micro Binfie Podcast]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:51:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Session 4 (6th May 2020)]]></title><description><![CDATA[With talks from Leonardo de Oliveira Martins, Inês Mendes and Rebecca Ansorge]]></description><link>https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-4</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time: 16:00 6 May 2020 (UTC) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom link: Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&quot;&gt;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:00 &lt;strong&gt;From phylogenetics to phylogenomics: between bacterial strains and the tree of life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Leonardo de Oliveira Martins  (Quadram Institute Bioscience)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:30 &lt;strong&gt;DEN-IM: dengue virus genotyping from amplicon and shotgun metagenomic sequencing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Inês Mendes (Instituto de Medicina Molecular)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:00 &lt;strong&gt;Same same but different: Functional diversity despite identical 16S rRNA sequences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Rebecca Ansorge (Quadram Institute Bioscience)   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:20 &lt;strong&gt;Virtual coffee break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From phylogenetics to phylogenomics: between bacterial strains and the tree of life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the amount and velocity of genomic data currently available, it became clear that no single gene, or even carefully selected gene sets, can provide a single evolutionary tree with confidence. We can therefore appreciate that apparently conflicting phylogenetic signals are not noise, but in fact reflect real biological phenomena ―  like duplications, lateral transfer, or ancestral polymorphisms. Phylogenomic models explicitly recognise this variation in evolutionary histories across the genome, allowing us to make most use of sequenced genomes. In this talk we will have an overview of popular models, as well as of emerging methodologies that can handle whole genomes from hundreds or thousands of samples.  We will also discuss favourite approaches in different fields, where the genomic sets may resemble closer a “tall” (fewer information from many samples) or a“wide” (fewer samples, with more information) data category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leomrtns.github.io&quot;&gt;https://leomrtns.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DEN-IM: dengue virus genotyping from amplicon and shotgun metagenomic sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dengue virus (DENV) represents a public health threat and economic burden in affected countries. The availability of genomic data is key to understanding viral evolution and dynamics, supporting improved control strategies. Currently, the use of high-throughput sequencing (HTS) technologies, which can be applied both directly to patient samples (shotgun metagenomics) and to PCR-amplified viral sequences (amplicon sequencing), is potentially the most informative approach to monitor viral dissemination and genetic diversity by providing, in a single methodological step, identification and characterization of the whole viral genome at the nucleotide level. Despite many advantages, these technologies require bioinformatics expertise and appropriate infrastructure for the analysis and interpretation of the resulting data. In addition, the many software solutions available can hamper the reproducibility and comparison of results. Here we present DEN-IM, a one-stop, user-friendly, containerized and reproducible workflow for the analysis of DENV short-read sequencing data from both amplicon and shotgun metagenomics approaches. It is able to infer the DENV coding sequence (CDS), identify the serotype and genotype, and generate a phylogenetic tree. It can easily be run on any UNIX-like system, from local machines to high-performance computing clusters, performing a comprehensive analysis without the requirement for extensive bioinformatics expertise. Using DEN-IM, we successfully analysed two types of DENV datasets. The first comprised 25 shotgun metagenomic sequencing samples from patients with variable serotypes and genotypes, including an in vitro spiked sample containing the four known serotypes. The second consisted of 106 paired-end and 76 single-end amplicon sequences of DENV 3 genotype III and DENV 1 genotype I, respectively, where DEN-IM allowed detection of the intra-genotype diversity. The DEN-IM workflow, parameters and execution configuration files, and documentation are freely available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/B-UMMI/DEN-IM&quot;&gt;https://github.com/B-UMMI/DEN-IM&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About the speaker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inês Mendes is currently a PhD student at Instituto de Medicina Molecular and University Medical Center Groningen.
Her formal education started, in 2011, in Cellular and Molecular Biology, in Faculdade de Ciências e Tecnologia - Universidade Nova de Lisboa, followed by a Master degree in 2014 in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology in Faculdade de Ciências - Universidade de Lisboa. Inês joined the Instituto de Medicina Molecular, at the Mário Ramirez Lab as a master student in 2015 where she used a variety of open source tools, and developed her own scripts, in Python, for the analysis of Streptococcus dysgalactiae genomes recovered from different sources (both human and animal). Since then, she remained a member of the MRamirez Lab as a Bioinformatician where I developed and maintain in house tools and scripts and perform various analysis using a variety of open source tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018 Inês began a PhD in Bioinformatics, in collaboration with University Medical Center Groningen, focused on metagenomics, validation and reproducibility, specially relevant when analyzing clinical data. Her work is supervised by Dr. João André Carriço and Prof. Dr. Mário Ramirez, from University of Lisbon, and Prof. Dr. John W A Rossen, from University of Groningen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Same same but different: Functional diversity despite identical 16S rRNA sequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 16S rRNA sequence is commonly considered a gold standard to determine the diversity in microbial communities. But how much diversity do we miss when we stop there? We investigated a low-diversity symbiosis between deep-sea bivalves and their bacterial symbionts using their metagenomic information. Despite identical 16S sequences we found as many as 16 intracellular symbiont strains to co-exist in single host individuals. We used nucleotide polymorphism and read coverage information to tease apart strain-level differences within symbiont populations. This approach revealed extensive differences in the gene content of these strains, that are otherwise unaccessible from the MAGs. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Session 3 (29nd April 2020)]]></title><description><![CDATA[With talks from Conor Meehan, Shatavia Morrison and Rebecca Bengtsson]]></description><link>https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-3</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-3</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time: 16:00 22 April 2020 (UTC) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom link: Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&quot;&gt;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:00 &lt;strong&gt;Discovery of a new lineage of Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/strong&gt;
Conor Meehan (University of Bradford)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:30 &lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning and Whole Genome Sequencing: Dragging classical method of Legionella pneumophila serotyping, kicking and screaming, into the 21st century&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Shatavia Morrison (CDC - NCIRD/DBD/RDB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:00 &lt;strong&gt;Combating shigellosis in endemic settings with pathogen genomics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Rebecca Bengtsson (The University of Liverpool)   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:20 &lt;strong&gt;Virtual coffee break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discovery of a new lineage of Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human- and animal-adapted lineages of the Mycobacterium tuberculosis complex (MTBC) are thought to have clonally expanded from a common progenitor in Africa. However, the molecular events that accompanied this emergence remain largely unknown. Here, we describe two MTBC strains isolated from patients with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis, representing an as-yet-unknown lineage, named Lineage 8 (L8), restricted to the African Great Lakes region. Using genome-based phylogenetic reconstruction, we show that L8 is a sister clade to the known MTBC lineages. Comparison with other complete mycobacterial genomes indicate that the divergence of L8 preceded the loss of the cobF genome region - involved in the cobalamin/vitamin B12 synthesis - and gene interruptions in a subsequent common ancestor shared by all other known MTBC lineages. This discovery further supports an East African origin for the MTBC and provides additional molecular clues on the ancestral genome reduction associated with adaptation to a pathogenic lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bradford.ac.uk/staff/cmeehan2&quot;&gt;https://www.bradford.ac.uk/staff/cmeehan2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Machine Learning and Whole Genome Sequencing: Dragging classical method of Legionella pneumophila serotyping, kicking and screaming, into the 21st century - About the speaker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented by Shatavia Morrison who is a Bioinformatician at the CDC (NCIRD/DBD/RDB) - Respiratory Diseases Branch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Combating shigellosis in endemic settings with pathogen genomic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Enteric Multicentre Study (GEMS) identified Shigella as one of the leading causes of moderate-to-severe diarrhoea in children across seven African and Asian countries. However, increasing antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and lack of a licensed vaccine, means that treatment and management options for shigellosis are limited. Whole-genome sequencing analysis (WGSA) can be effectively used to investigate AMR and epidemiological surveillance of Shigella, but this has yet to be applied in countries where childhood mortality rates are the highest and the disease is endemic. Here, we performed WGSA of Shigella isolates from GEMS (255 S. sonnei and 759 S. flexneri) to explore the implications of AMR and genetic diversity relating to vaccination, to improve interventions and management of shigellosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We detected multiple, independent acquisitions of mutations conferring reduced susceptibility to ciprofloxacin (the current recommended treatment) among isolates from Asia, reflecting selection due to heavy usage of the drug in these regions. While vaccination is a good alternative for management of shigellosis, we revealed implications which may impact the likely effectiveness of multiple approaches. These include, sequence variation within known epitopes of several antigen-vaccine candidates (eg. IpaB). Serotype switching, which may compromise immune protection induced by serotype-specific glycoconjugate vaccines. To help inform effective implementation of such vaccination programs, temporal analysis was used to estimate anticipated time frames over which serotype switching may lead to vaccine escape. In conclusion, WGSA of this representative dataset has provided valuable information to guide treatment and management of shigellosis through antimicrobial therapy and vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://baker-lab.github.io/&quot;&gt;https://baker-lab.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Session 2 (22nd April 2020)]]></title><description><![CDATA[With talks from Taylor Paisie, Federica Palma and Melinda Ashcroft]]></description><link>https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time: 16:00 22 April 2020 (UTC) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom link: Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&quot;&gt;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:00 &lt;strong&gt;Genomic Dynamics of Toxigenic Vibrio cholerae&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Taylor Paisie (University of Florida)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:30 &lt;strong&gt;Accessory genes located in mobile genetic elements drive the adaption to chemical biocides in Listeria monocytogenes evolutionary lineages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Federica Palma (ANSES)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:50 &lt;strong&gt;Whole genome sequencing reveals limited within-host variability in Neisseria gonorrhoeae from multiple anatomical sites&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Melinda Ashcroft (The Peter Doherty Institute of Infection and Immunity at The University of Melbourne)   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:20 &lt;strong&gt;Virtual coffee break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Genomic dynamics of toxigenic Vibrio cholerae - About the speaker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD Candidate studying the phylodynamics of Vibrio cholerae.  I received by bachelor’s degree in Biology from Florida State University.  My current projects include studying the evolution of V. cholerae in Haiti and the Democratic Republic of Congo.  I am interested in studying computational techniques and methods to help conduct phylodynamic analysis on whole genomes of infectious disease pathogens.  In my free time I enjoy your typical nerd activities, such as discussing Game of Thrones at great lengths and playing video games too late into the night (only on the weekends of course).  I also enjoy practicing yoga and being anywhere on the water in Florida.  Also, I love MY cats, Arya and Hamilton. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/taylorpaisie&quot;&gt;https://github.com/taylorpaisie&lt;/a&gt;
Twitter:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tpaisie&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/tpaisie&lt;/a&gt;
Linkedin:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/taylorpaisie/&quot;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/taylorpaisie/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessory genes located in mobile genetic elements drive the adaption to chemical biocides in Listeria monocytogenes evolutionary lineages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanitation practices are essential to reduce the risk of Listeria monocytogenes (Lm) contaminations along the food chain, yet the outstanding tolerance of some strains to biocides challenges food safety. This study aims to apply hybrid tools, implementing a combination of continuous phenotypes, statistical and phylogenomic methods, to characterize the Lm genomic determinants increasing tolerance to biocides used in the food industry at the pangenomic scale.
A genome-wide association study (GWAS) was performed on 188 strains isolated from ready-to-eat foods, wild and farm animals/environments. These strains were accurately selected from the wide collection of the research project LISTADAPT to encompass the genomic diversity of Lm clonal complexes (CC) observed in Europe. Generalized linear models with advanced correction for population structure considering homologous recombination events from the coregenome were used to test for associations between pangenomic orthologous genes (POG) and minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of eight biocides.
Strong causal associations (lrt-pvalue&amp;#x3C;4.69E-05 – Bonferroni correction at 5%) for benzalkonium chloride (BC) were identified in clusters of POGs depicting mobile genomic elements (MGE) like the Tn6188 transposon and pLMST6 plasmid. Increased tolerance to BC was previously described in Lm strains harbouring these MGEs. Visually inflated quantile-quantile plots from GWAS pointed to a cluster of 24 POGs, part of large plasmids known to be involved in Lm survival to food-processing stress, also associated to BC-tolerance at less stringent significance levels (lrt-pvalue&amp;#x3C;1.61E-04). Below this genome-wide significance level, the pLMST6 was also associated with didecyldimethylammonium chloride (DDAC), a quaternary ammonium compound (QAC) with bactericidal action similar to BC. As expected, no POGs were associated with chemically reactive biocides (e.g. hydrogen peroxide) and biocides that cause cytoplasmic proteins denaturation and cell contents coagulation (e.g. alcohol).
Accessory genomic determinants for increased MICs to BC and DDAC mainly characterized food strains from phylogenetically distant CCs collected across Europe, suggesting that these MGEs represent pleiotropic key-markers promoting and spreading QACs tolerance in Lm populations. Screening these MGEs could assist in improving decision-making for monitoring biocide-tolerant genotypes throughout the food chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About the speaker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Master degree in Food Science and Technology (2011-2014), I specialised in molecular typing of bacterial pathogens applied to Food Safety at the Department of Agriculture and Food Science of the University of Bologna (Italy). In my PhD (2014-2018), I trained in microbial genomics and bioinformatics, which became the main tools of my research activities. I, therefore, carried out international research projects within the objectives of the European project COMPARE (WP4 and 7) and in collaboration with the research team supported by the INNUENDO project under the supervision of Prof. Mirko Rossi. My thesis focused on the surveillance and persistence investigations of foodborne pathogens (e.g. Listeria monocytogenes and Salmonella enterica) along the food chain, in particular Italian swine chain and rabbit meat cutting plant, combining phenotypic and genomics methods. During my postdoctoral fellowships (2018-present) at the French agency for food safety (Maisons-Alfort lab, ANSES), I continued to apply advanced microbial genomic methods for (i) assessing the persistence and cold adaption of L. monocytogenes from ready-to-eat industries (ii) designing genome databases for the source attribution of monophasic S. Typhimurium (iii) implementing logistic regression models for source attribution based on accessory genes, and (iv) rapidly detecting outbreak-related foodborne pathogens using non-parametric tests. I currently manage collaborative research projects within the WP4 of the One Health EJP LISTADAPT focusing on the discovery of genomic features associated with antimicrobial resistance of L. monocytogenes combining phenotypic traits, phylogenomic and pangenome-wide association study. &lt;a href=&quot;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7865-961X&quot;&gt;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7865-961X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Whole genome sequencing reveals limited within-host variability in Neisseria gonorrhoeae from multiple anatomical sites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neisseria gonorrhoeae is a major public health threat due to increasing incidence and antimicrobial resistance. Mathematical modelling and genomic analyses are powerful methods for investigating transmission dynamics of N. gonorrhoeae; however, both approaches often make the implicit assumption that N. gonorrhoeae isolates at different anatomical sites within the same patient are the same strain, which may confound accurate assessment of evolution and transmission dynamics. This study examined a collection of N. gonorrhoeae isolates from 2011-2019 from patients that had N. gonorrhoeae detected at multiple anatomical sites. We used whole genome sequencing (WGS) and a variety of bioinformatic approaches (e.g. differing reference genomes and filtering of SNPs in repeats, mobile genetic elements and recombinant regions) to determine the within-host genetic diversity. Thirty-seven patients had cultured N. gonorrhoeae from two or more anatomical sites (urogenital, anorectal or oropharyngeal), with a final dataset of 105 isolates. In 35/37 (95%) patients, infections were the same strain, with identical MLST and NG-MAST profiles. Pairwise comparisons of the core-genome SNP alignment indicated that the median intra-patient SNP distance was zero SNPs, with a range of 0-18. Additionally, there were four groups of patient isolates that clustered together with identical MLST and a maximum pairwise SNP distances ≤18 SNPs, which was within the same range as the maximum within-host diversity, indicating the likelihood that patients within each cluster were involved in the same transmission network. Our data demonstrates that in most cases, the same strain of N. gonorrhoeae causes infection at multiple sites, however WGS data alone cannot differentiate between the same infecting strain or reinfections from the same transmission network. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About the speaker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Melinda Ashcroft was awarded her PhD from the University of Queensland, Australia in early 2019, investigating the roles of mobile genetic elements, antimicrobial resistance and DNA methylation in the evolution of Escherichia coli lineages. Melinda is now a Postdoctoral Research Fellow in Microbial Bioinformatics at the Peter Doherty Institute for Infection and Immunity at the University of Melbourne, Australia. Her work focuses on genomic epidemiology, transmission, evolution and antimicrobial resistance of pathogenic Neisseria spp. Melinda is also passionate about science communication and is a current Australian Society of Microbiology Communications Ambassador. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Session 1 (15th April 2020)]]></title><description><![CDATA[With talks from Zhemin Zhou, Dan Fornika and Dag Harmsen]]></description><link>https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://happykhan.github.io/conference2020//posts/session-1/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time: 16:00 15 April 2020 (UTC) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom link: Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&quot;&gt;https://discord.gg/WmuRbD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:00 &lt;strong&gt;EnteroBase: exploit core genomic diversity of bacterial pathogens&lt;/strong&gt;
Zhemin Zhou (University of Warwick)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:30 &lt;strong&gt;Intro to IRIDA Pipeline Plugins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dan Fornika (BCCDC Public Health Laboratory)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:00 &lt;strong&gt;cgMLST Re-visited: Evolvement and Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dag Harmsen (Univ. Münster, Germany)   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:30 &lt;strong&gt;Virtual coffee break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;EnteroBase: exploit core genomic diversity of bacterial pathogens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EnteroBase is an integrated software environment which supports the identification of global population structures within several bacterial genera. EnteroBase has currently assembled more than 400,000 genomes from Illumina short reads from Salmonella, Escherichia and five other bacterial genera, and genotyped most of these genomes by core genome Multilocus Sequence Typing (cgMLST). Hierarchical clustering of cgMLST sequence types allows mapping a new bacterial strain to predefined population structures at multiple levels of resolution and thus dynamic tracking of transmission chains. The interactive graphical user interface in EnteroBase eases the access of large scale bacterial genomic data and facilitates international data sharing and collaborations. I demonstrated the use of EnteroBase with multiple examples in Salmonella and Escherichia (30 mins)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zheminzhou&quot;&gt;https://github.com/zheminzhou&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro to IRIDA pipeline plugins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick intro to the IRIDA system (irida.ca), followed by brief discussion of how to develop your own ‘Pipeline Plugins’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Fornika is a Molecular Biologist + Bioinformatician = ‘Genomics Specialist’ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dfornika&quot;&gt;https://github.com/dfornika&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;cgMLST re-visited: Evolvement and challenges - About the speaker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dag Harmsen is an MD specialized in Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases Epidemiology. Since 2004 he holds a professorship at the Medical Faculty of the University Münster, Germany. His scientific interests focus around molecular diagnostics, epidemiology, and phylogeny of micro-organisms. He published the world-wide first study that applied the Bruker MALDI ToF MS system in microbiological diagnostics (JCM 2008; 46:1946). He earned quite some recognition for early real-time application of benchtop NGS sequencing and first application of what later become known as core genome MLST (cgMLST) genome-wide allele calling during the 2011 German STEC O104:H4 outbreak (PLoS ONE 2011; 6:e22751). More recently he published a highly noted NGS benchtop machine comparison (Nat Biotechnol 2013; 31:294). However, he is best known for delivering for more than 20 years popular applied microbiology bioinformatics solutions - like spa-typing for MRSA (JCM 2003; 41:5442) or the MIRU-VNTR service for M. tuberculosis typing (Nucleic Acids Res 2010; 38:W326).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harmsen is also co-founder (2003), shareholder, and co-managing director of Ridom GmbH (Münster, Germany). Ridom develops bioinformatics software (most notable StaphType and SeqSphere+) for clinical and public health microbiology sequence (Sänger and WGS) analysis. From 2005 until 2014 he was a member of the Executive Board of the ‘International Committee on Systematics of Prokaryotes’ (ICSP) of the International Union of Microbiological Societies (IUMS). From 2007 until July 2012 he served in the ‘Professional Development Committee’ of the American Society for Microbiology (ASM). Finally, Dr. Harmsen was technical advisor for NGS based surveillance of ECDC, EFSA, WHO, FAO, US Government Accountability Office, and US National Sciences Academy.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>